33 chapter 34 of Black Beauty this LibriVox recording is In the public
domain Black Beauty by Anna Su chapter 34 An Old
warhorse Captain had been broken in and trained for an army horse; his first
owner was an officer of cavalry going out to the Crimean war. He said he quite
enjoyed the training with all the other horses, trotting together, turning
together, to the right hand or the left, halting at the word of command, or
dashing forward at full speed at the sound of the trumpet or signal of the
officer. He was, when young, a dark, dappled iron gray and considered very
handsome. His master, a young, high-spirited gentleman, was very fond of
him, and treated him from the first with the greatest care and kindness. He told
me he thought the life of an army horse was very pleasant; but when it came to
being sent abroad over the sea in a great ship, he almost changed his mind.
“That part of it,” said he, “was dreadful! Of course we could not walk off the land
into the ship; so they were obliged to put strong straps under our bodies, and
then we were lifted off our legs in spite of our struggles, and were swung
through the air over the water, to the deck of the great
vessel. There we were placed in small close stalls, and never for a long time
saw the sky, or were able to stretch our legs. The ship sometimes rolled about in
high winds, and we were knocked about, and felt bad
enough. “However, at last it came to an end, and we were hauled up, and swung over
again to the land; we were very glad, and snorted and Ned for joy, when we once
more felt firm ground under our feet. “We soon found that the country we
had come to was very different from our own and that we had many hardships to
endure besides the fighting; but many of the men were so fond of their horses
that they did everything they could to make them comfortable in spite of snow,
wet, and all things out of order.” “But what about the fighting?” said I,
“was not that worse than anything else?” “Well,” said he, “I hardly know; we
always like to hear the trumpet sound, and be called out, and we're impatient to
start off, though sometimes we had to stand for hours, waiting for the word of
command; and when the word was given we used to spring forward as G and as
eagerly as if there were no cannonballs bayonets, or bullets. I believe so long as
we felt our rider firm in the saddle, and his hand steady on the bridle, not one of
us gave way to fear, not even when the terrible Bombshells whirled through the
air and burst into a thousand pieces. “I, with my noble master, went into
many actions together without a wound; and though I saw horses shot down with
bullets, pierced through with lances, and gashed with fearful saber Cuts though we
left them dead on the field, or dying in the agony of their wounds, I don't think
I feared for myself. My master's cheery voice, as he encouraged his men, made me
feel as if he and I could not be killed.
I had such perfect trust in him that while he was guiding me I was ready to
charge up to the very cannon's mouth. I saw many brave men cut down, many
fall mortally wounded from their saddles.
I had heard the cry and groans of the dying, I had caned over ground slippery
with blood, and frequently had to turn aside to avoid trampling on wounded man
or horse, but, until one dreadful day, I had never felt terror; that day I shall never
forget.” Here old Captain paused for a while and drew a long breath; I waited, and he went
on. “It was one autumn morning, and as usual, an hour before daybreak our
cavalry had turned out, ready comparison for the day's work, whether it might be fighting or
waiting. The men stood by their horses waiting, ready for orders. As the light
increased there seemed to be some excitement among the officers; and before
the day was well begun we heard the firing of the enemy's
guns. “Then one of the officers rode up and gave the word for the men to mount,
and in a second every man was in his saddle, and every horse stood expecting
the touch of the rain or the pressure of his rider's heels, all animated, all eager;
but still we had been trained so well that, except by the champing of our bits,
and the restive tossing of our heads from time to time, it could not be said that we
stirred. “My dear master and I were at the head of the line, and as all sat
motionless and watchful, he took a little stray lock of my man which had turned
over on the wrong side, laid it over on the right, and smoothed it down with his
hand; then patting my neck, he said, 'We shall have a day of it today Bayard, my
beauty; but we'll do our duty as we have done.' He stroked my neck that morning
more, I think, than he had ever done before; quietly on and on, as if he were
thinking of something else. I love to feel his hand on my neck, and arched my
crest proudly and happily; but I stood very still, for I knew all his moods, and
when he liked me to be quiet, and when gay. “I cannot tell all that happened on
that day, but I will tell of the last charge that we made together; it was
across a valley right in front of the enemy's cannon. By this time we were well
used to the roar of heavy guns, the rattle of musket fire, and the flying of
shot near us; but never had I been under such a fire as we rode through on that
day. From the right, from the left, and from from the front, shot and shell
poured in upon us. Many a brave man went down, many a horse fell, flinging his
rider to the earth; many a horse without a rider ran wildly out of the ranks; then
terrified at being alone, with no hand to guide him, came pressing in among his old
companions, to gallop with them to the charge. “Fearful as it was, no one stopped,
no one turned back. Every moment the ranks were thinned, but as I comrades
fell, we closed in to keep them together; and instead of being shaken or staggered
in our pace our gallop became faster and faster as we neared the
cannon. “My master, my dear master was cheering on his comrades with his right
arm raised on high, when one of the balls whizzing close to my head struck him. I
felt him stagger with the shock, though he uttered no cry; I tried to check my
speed, but the sword dropped from his right hand, the rain fell loose from the
left, and sinking backward from the saddle he fell to the earth; the other
riders swept past us, and by the force of their charge I was driven from the
spot. “I wanted to keep my place by his side and not leave him under that rush
of horses' feet, but it was in vain; and now without a master or a friend I was
alone on that great slaughter ground; then fear took hold on me too and I
trembled as I had never trembled before; and I too, as I had seen other horses do,
tried to join in the ranks and gallop with them; but I was beaten off by the
swords of the soldiers. Just then a soldier whose horse had been killed under him caught at my
Bridal and mounted me, and with this new master I was again going forward; but our
gallant company was cruy overpowered, and those who remained alive after the
fierce fight for the guns came galloping back over the same
ground. Some of the horses had been so bad wounded that they could scarcely
move from the loss of blood; other noble creatures were trying on three legs to
drag themselves along, and others were struggling to rise on their forefeet
when their hind legs had been shattered by shot. After the battle the wounded men
were brought in and the dead were
buried.” “And what about the wounded horses?” I said; “were they left to
die?” “No, the army farers went over the fields with their pistols and shot all
that were ruined; some that had only slight wounds were brought back and
attended to, but the greater part of the noble, willing creatures that went out
that morning never came back! In our stables there was only about one in four that
returned. “I never saw my dear master again. I believe he fell dead from the
saddle. I never loved any other master so well. I went into many other engagements,
but was only once wounded, and then not seriously; and when the war was over I
came back again to England, as sound and strong as when I went
out.” I said, “I have heard people talk about war as if it were a very fine
thing.” “Ah!” said he, “I should think they never saw it. No doubt it is very fine
when there is no enemy, when it is just exercise and parade and sham fight. Yes,
it is very very fine then; but when thousands of good brave men and horses
are killed or crippled for life, it has a very different
look.” “Do you know what they fought about?” said I. “No,” he said, “that is more than a
horse can understand, but the enemy must have been awfully wicked people, if it
was right to go all that way over the sea on purpose to kill
them end of chapter 34